<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Protestant antidote against Popery with a brief discourse of the great atheisticalness and vain amours now in fashion. Written in a letter to a young lady. By a Person of Honour.</title>
            <author>Person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2054:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Protestant antidote against Popery with a brief discourse of the great atheisticalness and vain amours now in fashion. Written in a letter to a young lady. By a Person of Honour.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>179, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed; and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde, bookseller in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Gathered in sixes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36427:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Proteſtant Antidote Againſt POPERY: With A Brief DISCOURSE of the great Atheiſticalneſs and vain AMOURS now in Faſhion.</p>
            <p>Written in a LETTER to a Young Lady.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed; And are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36427:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36427:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know the Law of Cuſtom has made it not onely an uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al favour, but an expected Duty, to comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at leaſt, if not flatter, ſuch women as men write to, eſpecially the Great Ladies, who think none write well, that do not praiſe them much, and thoſe write beſt, who extol them moſt:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36427:3"/>High praiſes being like good Poetry, Muſick in words, the ſound of which may be agreeable, but truly to deſerve them, requires ſuch a Gygantick ſize of merit, as is very unproportionable to the ſlender-waſted Virtues of moſt Ladies, who are over-eager to receive praiſes, and over-careleſs in meriting any, and the grand reaſon is, becauſe they know they uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have them without it, and that cuſtom muſt give it, though reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſo obliging is the common courteſie of <hi>England</hi> to Ladies, that it allows them to pretend to all praiſes as their due, though few deſerve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36427:3"/>any as their right. In a word, our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladies muſt have their Characters writ, juſt as the <hi>Dutch</hi> Madams will have their Pictures drawn, that is very handſom, though they themſelves be never ſo ugly.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> for your part, I know your perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo abundantly, and my own heart ſo truly, as I muſt beg the Law of Cuſtom par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don here, it being beyond my power to flatter, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, ſince I can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther overpraiſe your high me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or out-ſpeak the real love, and true eſteem, I have both for you and them, ſo that knowing all manner of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be juſtly due to your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36427:4"/>I find I cannot here make you a preſent of any, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing you an injurie, by intituling you to thoſe praiſes by gift, which all know are your own by right.</p>
            <p>For truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> the whole progreſs of your Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have ſtill been ſo highly vertuous, and religiouſly ſtrict, and ever believed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed ſuch, that though your Beautie might make bad men wiſh you ill, yet your Vertues hinder the worſt from daring to think you ſo; for if they did, their own hearts muſt at the ſame time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their own thoughts, and declare your innocencie; like <hi>Pilate,</hi> who with the ſame
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36427:4"/>breath he condemned our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſaid, <hi>He found no fault in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> though your vertuous life is ſo tranſparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellent, yet for all that, you ought to look on your unſoil'd reputation as no ſmall bleſſing of preſervation in theſe ſcandalous times, where ſo few Handſom Ladies eſcape cenſure, and ſo many deſerve it; for now the extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Romance-Amours are not onely daily read, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hourly practiſed; and women act, more than Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances can write, whilſt the ſober rules of Vertue, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties of Religion, are ſeldom thought on, and moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36427:5"/>rarely practiſed, our Youth being generally grown, ſuch fond friends of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his Books, as they are become meer ſtrangers to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Goſpel, they living as if they were all bodies, and had no ſouls, or had them but to loſe, turning Religion into Raillerie, and Goſpet into Romance; for thus in ſhort they mangle Scripture, that part which is chiefly Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, that is their meer Goſpel-part; and that which is the Goſpel-part, is their meer Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical-part; and becauſe they cannot bring the Goſpel to prove their Atheiſtical rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, pretend to prove by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that there is no Goſpel;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36427:5"/>and if ſome of them now and then look over a Chapter, they onely paſs through it, as a Spie doth an Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, with a miſchievous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and if they can but find in Scripture a ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that they preſently bring on the Stage, as they do Fools in Plays, to raillie with, and make ſport at; ſo great a Jeaſt our Young Sparks now make of their ſalvation, as to be pleas'd in the meer diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, without conſidering 'tis not onely Atheiſtical mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Deviliſh follie, to make that their Jeſt which they may be damn'd for in Earneſt.</p>
            <p>Thus our Youth throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36427:6"/>way their ſouls, and for their time they care not how they ſpend it, (alwaies provided it be not religiouſly) and therefore they waſt it moſt in the companie of vain women, and are ſo eager and zealous in their purſuit, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in their ſervice, as if they fancied God was miſtaken, and intended creating man for the woman, rather than the woman for the man; but though all know God made the woman for the man: Yet what Critick can tell us whether our new-mode has made the Gallant for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, or the Miſtreſs for the Gallant; but of this we are all ſure, they are ſo plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36427:6"/>made for one another, that the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Country Laws al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not with more freedom pluralitie of Wives, than our new-<hi>Engliſh</hi> Cuſtoms admit pluralitie of Miſtreſſes; Nay, I may yet venture to ſay more, That the Libertie of our men exceeds theirs; for they are permitted no more Wives, than they can well keep, but ours are allowed as many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes as they can any way get.</p>
            <p>For indeed the Names of <hi>Tom</hi> and <hi>Beſs</hi> are hardly more familiar here, than thoſe of Gallant and Miſtreſs, and are ſo far from being eſteemed Names of diſcredit, that many of our Mode Ladies look on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36427:7"/>their Gallants as Beauty-marks, rather than ſtains of Reputation, and for all they cannot but know, that the infection of Gallants is as bad an enemy to credit, as the ſmall Pox to Beautie, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ruiner of it; And though womens Gallants are in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> no better than the publick Executioners of their reputations, and indeed no women will allow them, but ſuch as are willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to ſuffer (and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that ſlight reputation are ſeldom fond of Chaſtitie) Yet theſe abuſers of love, &amp; murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of fame, by their fair words and baſe Arts have ſo inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves into their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36427:7"/>as the women now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, call their Gallants their Friends, and if common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port port may be credited, they are indeed their boſom-ones; (and ſuch women as value lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle what others ſay, ſeldome care much what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do) Cuſtome having brought many of our women to that paſs, as they now glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the number of their Gallants, eſteeming them rather ſo many Vouchers of their Beautie, than ſo many robbers of their Honour, the ſo uſual practice of this ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, having taken away wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſenſe, that like black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs amongſt the <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> its commoneſs has removed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36427:8"/>its deformitie: And there is now ſuch a forward Love-ſpring in the Nurſeries of our Young Ladies, as the very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones learn to ſpell Amour with their Feſcue, and will pretend to entertain their Young Gallants, in the dark walks of Love, and in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth of its Intrigues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they well know what the thing Love is, or the name of Gallant means, and would have Servants come to them, before they come to the Teens, (the ripeneſs of their minds outrunning that of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) and fancy men ſo mad as to believe, 'tis expectation makes a Bleſſing dear; but that dull Preſbyterian way
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36427:8"/>of Love, is now quite out of Faſhion, &amp; the loves of our Young Gallants are grown as fickle and meer ſkin deep, as their Miſtreſſes Fancies and Beauties; and Love-wounds that are but ſkin deep, can never hurt the heart; and therefore though every day we hear of Hundreds of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants that are dying for love in their Miſtreſſes companie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet we cannot read of one theſe many Ages that dyed for Love in the Weekly Bills of Mortalitie, the obliging carriage of the Ladies of the times having made our Young men ſo healthfully wiſe, ſo forwardly bold, or at leaſt ſo impatiently haſtie, as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36427:9"/>now a dayes to take Young women, as great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies do weak Towns, onely by Summons, or Aſſaults, as not eſteeming them worthy the time and trouble of a Love-ſiege, though their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes were as yielding as <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, which Writers ſay, was never beſieged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being taken: that is in ſhort, they hold Handſome women worth enjoying, but not wooing. And that makes our Young men ſo eager and inconſtant in their Amours, as really 'tis a very hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring-caſt to tell, whether our Young Gallants uſe now more art, or ſpeed, in the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or forgetting of their Miſtreſſes.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36427:9"/>
            <p>But the beſt of it is, that the inconſtancie of both Sexes are now ſo equally match'd, that I cannot write more of their Gallants inconſtancies, than their Miſtreſſes make good of their own; for they deal with their Gallants, as their Faſhions, that which comes lateſt is ſtill like'd beſt, and us'd moſt In a word, the conſtancie and inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of our Young men and women, are juſt like water, and ice, where one ſtill makes the other, and their loves (ice-like) never laſt long, and as ſoon as 'tis diſſolv'd, turns im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the ſame it was before, without any alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or prejudice: Nor can wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36427:10"/>be more apt and readie by the coming of Froſt to turn to ice, than our Young men and womens hearts are apt &amp; enclin'd to return to love, at the approach of freſh-fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied Beauty. And truly the inconſtancie of our Young men cannot be ſo great, nor their inclinations ſo ill, but the tongues of many of our Young women are grown as bad; for now if a Young maid be but cry'd up for handſom, and reſolves to continue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and therefore will not turn vain, and deſerve cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as much as the reſt, they will be ſure to ſpeak her as bad as the worſt, and if they cannot with Juſtice wound
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36427:10"/>her vertue, they will attempt by ill Arts to murder her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, (envie being the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of wicked invention) it being now a Mode principle amongſt moſt of our handſom women, that no woman that enjoyes a large proportion of Beautie, but muſt as an una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable appurtenance, carry with it a load of ſcandalous cenſures (a falſe Character of ſome, though too true a one of moſt) which occaſions their not caring how unjuſtly they increaſe anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, in hope to leſſen their own load, and by overſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſcarriages of others greater than they ſhould be, hope to ſhrink theirs leſs than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36427:11"/>really they are, vainly fancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by ſpattering with dirt and reproach other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens reputations, were a kind of wiping clean their own, which ſuits not at all with the mild and moderate rules of Vertue, which onely allows women to correct each others faults, by their good Examples, but not to increaſe them by their bad cenſures: For, ſcandalous cenſures like Muſhroms grow without any root, ſo tender, and mutable a thing, is a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom womans good Name: there's no taking its true Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by any certain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Rules and meaſures, Since it depends more on her
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36427:11"/>Neighbours good or bad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, than on her own vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or ill actions; &amp; more on what they ſay, than what ſhe does; &amp; really ſuch reports are uſually ſo ſophiſticated with ſelf concerns, and ſo ſtrongly byaſs'd by averſion or inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as you may daily hear in common Diſcourſe, both men and women turn vertue into vice, and vice into vertue; and ſo characterize Good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be bad, and bad wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be good, ſpeaking not as women deſerve, but as they fancy; and therefore it often happens, that many women ſave their reputations even by a ſpeedy loſing their chaſtity, whilſt other women loſe their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36427:12"/>reputation in their very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it, that is in ſhort, more women loſe their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in admitting to be much courted (though that be all) than by being in injoy'd, and the reaſon is plain, becauſe the courtſhip is publick to all, but the injoyment is onely private to themſelves, and 'tis more rational Two concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons ſhould keep their own councel, than many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd ſhould keep it for them; ſo that it cannot neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow, that the report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reputation or diſreputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of handſom women muſt needs be the true iſſue of their merits, but often the by-blow of chance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36427:12"/>common report can be no right rule to meaſure womens reputations by, for many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports have much of the Devils nature in them, who is a liar from the beginning. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if we but truly conſider, we ſhall find women general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure one another, not as they are really faultie, but as they appear, and are eſteemed handſome; and therefore ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women have the priviledge of Popes, who cannot err, but may do what they will, and take what libertie they pleaſe, and handſom women will be as far from cenſuring their actions, as young men from praiſing their perſons, ſo that really in effect, we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36427:13"/>find moſt womens cenſures are not proportionable to the ill, others act, but rather ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the beautie they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, which by their leave is a way of judging, that's both irrational and uncharitable; ſince I am ſure none can deny, but that there are ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſom women, unchaſt; and ſome chaſt women hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, for vertue and beautie are not ſo declar'd enemies, but they ſometimes meet; though I cannot deny, but that vertue which in former Ages was eſteemed one of the greateſt adornments of the ſoul, is now ſo Eclipſed by the outward beautie of the bodie, as vertue and piety
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36427:13"/>the true inward beautie) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhine out: a good ſoul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing now in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a good face, beautie being now the Great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that commands the whole World, and makes very Kings to un-King them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and become ſubjects to her. And yet this ſo ador'd beautie, (which all women are ſo ambitious of, and all men ſo court) has at beſt no intrinſick value in it, but juſt like riches, they enjoy moſt, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with leaſt; ſince 'tis not much, but enough, that's the true meaſure of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis now more than time to beg your pardon, for I find I am ſtray'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36427:14"/>both beyond the time, and beſide the road of my deſign'd Diſcourſe, which is not to preſent you a Character, or Liſt of the fine Ladies, and mode-vices of the times, they will require a much wittier Pen than I pretend to be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tter of, and a larger Volume than I deſign to trouble you with: but this Character which indeed merits volumes of praiſes, I am ſure I can give you without needing wit, or abuſing of time; and if I could here caſt up the ſumme total of all the vices that your Sex are either guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of, or ſcandaliz'd with, (which I'le aſſure you are more than a few) their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36427:14"/>might be tedious to read, but need not be diſagreeable for you to hear, ſince by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all thoſe faults, they are infected with, I ſhould but tell all thoſe you are free from.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> my deſign is now to remove my Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and change my Scene of Writing, as you have your place of Living, and to level my Diſcourſe, not at the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and pleaſures of <hi>London,</hi> nor the paſtimes of the Court, but at your Country Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; the Woods and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Macroome,</hi> which renders it a place much fitter to exerciſe your patience, than ſatisfie your delight,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36427:15"/>were you of the humour of moſt Ladies; but all know you are not onely an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent woman, but an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Wife, I mean in Goodneſs, (for 'tis rare now to meet a Wife that's not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary) for you take as much ſatisfaction in the cares of well managing and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving your Eſtate, as moſt other Ladies delight, in the laviſhing theirs, ſo that I can truly ſay, you have not onely brought your Lord a large ſumme of money for your Portion, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued increaſe of Rent by your Induſtrie.</p>
            <p>And I am ſure, <hi>Madam,</hi> if you were now aſk't as the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36427:15"/>Philoſopher was, Where was his home; you would anſwer now, as he did then, My home is ſtill where my chief buſineſs is. ſo that now your chief concerns and Family, (which is ſtill the good Wives Treaſure) being at <hi>Macroome,</hi> I muſt conclude your heart is there alſo.</p>
            <p>A place where in lieu of <hi>London,</hi> crowds of good Company, &amp; ſwarms of diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements; you muſt prepare to meet with, and do penance to your ſelf, among the Flocks of Prieſts and Fryers, againſt whoſe Popiſh inſinuations, and infectious perſwaſions, I here preſent you a ſmall, but neceſſary Collection of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36427:16"/>to carry about you, as a preſervative in your own Religion, and an Antidote againſt theirs; and though I cannot pretend this pocket Piſtol is a ſufficient Battering piece, to beat down their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Church, yet I doubt not but it will at leaſt be a ſufficient Life-guard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you and your Chamber againſt their aſſaults.</p>
            <p>They are moſt of them ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative reaſonings I pickt out of Mr. <hi>Chilling-worth,</hi> as one that reaſons beſt, and ſatisfies me moſt, of any I ever read; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you want a Collection of choice flowers, I heartily wiſh that theſe I have gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36427:16"/>out of his Garden, and here ſorted and made up to preſent you in a Noſegay, may ſerve you againſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſavour of Popiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and I wiſh they may not altogether degenerate from the common nature of flowers, which the Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt tells us, grow larger and better by being tranſplanted: ſo that I hope you will not find them the worſe, nor like them the leſs, for being tranſplanted, but receive theſe Arguments juſt as you do your Rents, without ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whether your Tenants have the Money out of their own bags, or borrow it; ſo you have it to ſupply
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36427:17"/>your occaſions.</p>
            <p>Truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> I have taken ſome pains, and ſpent much time in reading the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the Papiſts againſt our Religion, and though I have conſider'd their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without the leaſt Byas, or antedated prejudice; yet I can give no better a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of them, than I do of ill Dealers, the more I have to do with them, the worſe I like them: they ſavour much of ſelf-intereſt, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Goſpel Obedience, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs their holding Marriage a greater crime in a Prieſt than Fornication, the one is but forbid by their Churches
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36427:17"/>Law, which they all know is diſputable, the later by the Law of Chriſt, which they cannot but know, ought to be paſt all diſpute.</p>
            <p>And truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> if you pleaſe to admit your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to make but a ſhort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs into the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you ſhall find much to create your wonder, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to ſatisfie your reaſon or belief; for the Goſpel of Chriſt; is the Goſpel of Truth, and therefore ought ſtill to be pictur'd naked as Truth, without any Art of <hi>Roman</hi> Dreſſes, which are onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure ſhadings of the true light of Scripture, by making dark Paraphraſes on the plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36427:18"/>Goſpel Commands, which in all reaſon ought to be plain enough for the meaneſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; for God forbid it ſhould be otherwiſe, for the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chriſtian muſt be ſaved or damned, for keeping or not keeping them; and ſure God's Juſtice will never ſend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Hell, for not doing what they could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand was his Will, they ſhould do; that were ſuch a cruelty, as if a man ſhould torment his ſervant for not doing his Errant, when he knew he did not underſtand his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; yet the Papiſt muſt not take theſe plain Goſpel Commands as ſuch, but as they are diſtill'd in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36427:18"/>politick Lymbeck of the Popiſh intereſt: indeed My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and Obedience is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven in that Religion, that Papiſts muſt take what their Prieſt tells them, as men do wives, for better, for worſe, and muſt marry their Faith to their Churches infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, which allows that onely to be Goſpel which their Church ſayes ſhall be, not what the Apoſtles write is ſo; for the Papiſts muſt obey the Pope, though no where commanded in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; but muſt not read the Goſpel, though they are commanded there to do it.</p>
            <p>Nay, when once the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt can but touch the ſmall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36427:19"/>Needle of any ones reaſon with the Great Loadſtone of the Harmonious Doctrine of a neceſſary Obedience to their infallible Church, then they make ſuch follow it, to every point of the Compaſs, be it good, bad, or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; and ſo they ſail all their life, in a Trade-wind of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſuperſtition, and muſt belive their Prieſts words before their own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the plaineſt objects of them; as in the Miracle of Tranſubſtantiation, where you muſt have eyes and ſee not, hands and feel not, but muſt believe in a moment real Bread and Wine to be turned into perfect Fleſh and Blood,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36427:19"/>though you cannot ſee the leaſt change whatſoever, yet they are bound to belive their Prieſt, before their eyes, ſmell, or taſte, nor dare their Prieſt ſay, that the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bread (which they eſteem the real Body of Chriſt) will be leſs mouldie, or more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain of corruption after Conſecration than before; and the jeaſt of it is, that at the ſame time the Papiſts believe that Miracle, they alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Scripture, <hi>That God will not ſuffer his Holy One to ſee corruption.</hi> And though for theſe and many other reaſons, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Tranſubſtantiation-Miracle, yet I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36427:20"/>this Miracle that belongs to Tranſubſtantiation, which is, how the Pope can bring ſo many, that have ſenſe and reaſon, to believe it.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall paſs by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oring this Sacrament, their praying to Saints, and a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their ſuperſtitious obſervances never uſed in the primitive Church; and ſhall onely deſire you, <hi>Madam,</hi> to obſerve in general, that the Papiſts follow the Goſpel, juſt as they read <hi>Hebrew,</hi> that's backward; for God plainly commands, that all ſhould ſearch the Scripture. And our Bleſſed Saviour or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Sacrament to be adminiſtred in both kinds,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36427:20"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> forbids publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in an unknown Language, but that which is moſt for Edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 <hi>c.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>v.</hi> But theſe plain poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive commands do not hinder the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that unlearned men ſhall not read and ſearch the Scriptures; but if we believe St. <hi>Paul</hi> before the Pope, we may read in the 17. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> how he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Noble <hi>Bereans</hi> for ſearching the Scriputes, and therefore if ſearching the Scriptures had not been not onely lawful, but a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable act, certainly St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36427:21"/>them for ſo doing. So that the Popiſh Clergy forbids the reading the Scriptures, under a pretence that their Laity might not truly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. Next, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> allows onely their Clergy (except free Princes, for they are excepters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, though God is not) to receive the Communion but in one kind, though our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour commands, that all drink of the Cup; and the Papiſts cannot deny, but that the Communion was taken in both kinds in all Chriſtian Churches for above a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, for the poor vulgar ſort, they ſhall onely
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36427:21"/>hear their publick prayers in an unknown Tongue, <hi>viz. Latine,</hi> which a Tenth part of them do not underſtand; and therefore how that can be moſt for Edification, let the Papiſts tell if they can, I am ſure we cannot, nor do we believe they can; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of another Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation-Miracle, and make an unknown Language to moſt, to be chang'd at the ſame time into a common known Language to all.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> I ſhall humbly deſire you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in general, that though the Papiſts do out-noiſe us: (as ſhallow rivers do ſtill the the deepeſt) with the high
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36427:22"/>and mighty Rodomontades of their Churches infallibilitie; yet ſuch high Rants, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true proof, are but like School-boyes paper-Kites, which ſoar high and loftie, but have nothing elſe worth taking notice of. They will have the confidence to tell you, that their Popiſh Church is the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, and onely true Chriſtian Church in the whole world: But the Proteſtants Anſwer to this their boaſting, is, that all the Chriſtian Churches in the whole world (beſides, the Popiſh Churches) though more in number than they) declare quite contrary. They will aſk you, where your
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36427:22"/>Proteſtant Church was before <hi>Luther,</hi> which was wittily anſwered by one; (where the Papiſt Church never was) in the Bible.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts do divert themſelves very much at our ſtiling our King, <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> as we do, for their doing ſo, for we eſteem our King, Head onely in his own Dominions, without the Popes title of infallible; and ſure 'tis more rational that thoſe of a Kingdom ſhould allow their King to be <hi>Head of the Church</hi> in his own Kingdoms, than that a few Cardinals ſhould make the <hi>Head of the Church</hi> over all Kingdoms, And for all their Jeaſting, I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36427:23"/>am ſure we can ſhew (in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber earneſt) Scripture-preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for Kings being Heads of Churches in their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which is more than the papiſts can ſhew for their Pope, or his Churches infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libilitie: for ſure they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not object againſt it as new Doctrine (though Doctrine that's new is their greateſt Trade) that the Kings of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and the firſt Chriſtian Emperors were Heads of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Churches and in their own Dominions: And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tells us, <hi>That a Divine Sentence is in the lips of the King, and his mouth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth not in Judgement</hi> (which I am ſure Popes have
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36427:23"/>not, witneſs <hi>Liberius</hi>) and <hi>Solomon</hi> gives the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Heart of the King is in the Hand of the Lord. If the Papiſts will pretend ſo much Scripture for their Pope, I ſhall onely anſwer, 'Tis more than ever Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants read, or the Apoſtles writ.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts will tell you with a great deal of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that though we ſay the Bible is the Religion of Proteſtants, yet there is no Proteſtant Religion, or Church, mentioned in the whole Creed, which are the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: and they will tell you, that their Church is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36427:24"/>Church, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Catholick Church was an Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith from the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie of the Church in the beginning of the Apoſtles time, Now let the Papiſts tell us, if they bring this as an Argument againſt the Proteſtant Religion in the Bible, or not; if not, what cauſe have they to name it, or what need have we to anſwer it; but if it be one, we make this reply, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is no more named in the Apoſtles Creed, than the Proteſtant Church is; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the Apoſtles Creed was made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was a Church, and this I am ſure
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36427:24"/>they cannot deny; ſo that ſince the Catholick Church was then in being, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church not in being, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Catholick Church mentioned in the Apoſtles Creed, and conſequently is not the Mother-Church, as the Papiſts would have her to be: thus the Papiſts have ſo overcharg'd this Argument to ſhoot at us, as it recoils and flyes in their own faces.</p>
            <p>And of kin to this, is their grand Battering piece of all, which ſo thunders in the ears of all Papiſts, and makes the Popes power ſo abſolute, and the poor credulous Papiſt ſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36427:25"/>obedient, and that is the power given by our Saviour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the 16th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> beginning the 18th verſe. <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and on this Rock I will build my Church, and give thee the Keyes of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and whomſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> and theſe words the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts underſtand literally, that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon is the Rock that Chriſt builds his Church on, which cannot poſſibly be, by the <hi>verſes</hi> juſt <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> for there when <hi>our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> tells his Diſciples <hi>of his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36427:25"/>going to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>where he muſt ſuffer many things, and be killed, and raiſed again the Third day;</hi> Peter <hi>took him, and began to rebuke him; be it far from thee, Lord, this ſhall not be unto thee:</hi> But our Saviour turned, and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan, thou art an offence to me, for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but thoſe that be of men.</hi> By which words 'tis moſt clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that our Saviour did not mean <hi>Peters</hi> perſon could be the Rock of the Chriſtian Church; for if <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon had been that Rock meant, ſure our Saviour would never have removed it behind him;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36427:26"/>and it would be not onely ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational, but impious, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Chriſt would build his Church on Satan, for ſo he calls St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon; and 'twere as unreaſonable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Rock of Chriſts Church could be an offence to him as St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon was, and as improbable again as all this, that Chriſts Church, the Foundation of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, ſhould ſavour, not of the things that be of God, but thoſe that are of men, as <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon did.</p>
            <p>Therefore if you will but pleaſe to read the words of our Saviour carefully, you ſhall find they are moſt plain, for <hi>verſe</hi> 13th. <hi>When Jeſus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36427:26"/>came into the Coaſt of</hi> Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, <hi>He ask'd his Diſciples, Whom do men ſay that I am, and they ſaid, Some ſay that thou art</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt, ſome</hi> Elias, <hi>and others</hi> Jeremias, <hi>or one of the Prophets, but whom ſay ye that I am; and</hi> Simon Peter <hi>anſwered and ſaid, Thou art Chriſt the Son of the Living God: And I ſay alſo unto thee, that thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and vpon this Rock,</hi> (not this perſon) <hi>I will build my Church, that is</hi> (upon this Rock of Faith) <hi>that I am Chriſt the Son of the Living God, I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt it.</hi> Now this muſt neceſſarily relate to his faith,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36427:27"/>not his perſon; for the gates of Hell, that's the power of evil, did prevail againſt <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s perſon, or he had not deny'd and forſworn his. Lord and Maſter again and again; and been afterwards proved blame-worthy by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his face, and indeed as blame-worthy as any of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; ſo that 'tis moſt plain, that Chriſts words (of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him the Rock of the Chriſtian Church) related not to his perſon, but his faith of Chriſts being the Son of the Living God.</p>
            <p>And for the other part; whereas the Papiſts believe a particular favour and power, given by our Saviour to S <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:36427:27"/>of the Keys of Heaven; that was given as much to the Eleven Diſciples, as to him, as you may read in the 18th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> &amp; in the 20th of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, and the 23, 24. verſes; <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, even ſo ſend I you, and when he had ſaid this, he breathed on them, and ſaith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſins ye remit, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them, and whoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> So that you ſee this power is general, to the Diſciples, and not in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> more than to any of the reſt, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts miſ-believe.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36427:28"/>
            <p>The Papiſts have many ſuch Queſtions, which I am ſure, <hi>Madam,</hi> you have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the patience to read, nor I the time to write, but thoſe that are moſt material of them you will find, I have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented you, truly anſwer'd, by pure Scripture, clear rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, plain arguments, and all in few words, fit for the weakeſt memory, or ſmalleſt pocket, to carry about them: for true reaſon doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in large Volumes, long Gowns, or gray Beards; for many live to One and Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without attaining to years of diſcretion; the degrees of Age being not ſtill the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſedom, for the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36427:28"/>world will never be without old Fools, and young Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers.</p>
            <p>And truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> for my part, I cannot ſo much as think of the Papiſts Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion without wonder, that ſo many rational men of them ſhould rather faſten their faith of ſalvation on the pretended infallibility of their Church (which is deny'd by moſt Chriſtians) than on the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, which is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all, to be the Will and Word of God; and the very Foundation of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Foundation, as contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it all things neceſſary to our ſalvation. And we Proteſtants have at leaſt this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36427:29"/>ſatisfaction and advantage, that not onely the Papiſts, but all ſorts of Chriſtians that are in the circumference of the whole world, meet and joyn with us in this centre of Faith, that the Scriptures contain all things neceſſary to our ſalvation; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a general granted Truth, I confeſs, I admire, how any Papiſt can make the leaſt ſcruple, which is the ſafeſt Heavenly Guide, the Pope or the Goſpel: If there be any rational man ſo extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant as to put them in the ſame ballance, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a rape upon his reaſon, I ſhall onely deſire him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this plain Queſtion; If
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36427:29"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he were to go a Journey in an unknown way, would he not think it more rational and ſafe to follow a certain true Guide, that all the Chriſtians in the world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, is certainly able and ready to ſhew him the right way, than to follow a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Guide, which the greateſt part of the Chriſtians in the world aſſures him will lead him out of it; And this being the real difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Papiſt and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in Groſs, concerning the Heavenly Guide, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the Pope, I think I need now ſay no more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many have already ſaid ſo much, and I am ſure
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36427:30"/>enough, to ſatisfie any, except ſuch, who will believe a crooked Rule is better, to draw a ſtraight line by, than a right one.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Madam</hi> I ſhall onely beg, ſo much of your patience as to let me tell you, that the plot and Heads of this following diſcourſe, I have Extracted out of the worthy <hi>Chilingworth.</hi> Before I begin the diſcourſe it ſelf; I know in writing a play, to have Rank'd the plot in the Front of it, and to make the whole deſign of the Prologue to be the Key, to uncipher the plot of the play, (though anciently in uſe) had been now, not onely out of faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36427:30"/>but beſide reaſon; For the deſign of plays, aiming chiefly to pleaſe the ſenſes, they ought to be compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and mixt with hopes and fears, certainties, and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties, Expectations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays of the event of the plot; which being all ſo interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven together, creates the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeableneſs of the play; for when once the whole plot is diſcovered, the pleaſure of the play is ended; like Hare-Hunting, the ſport lies not in preſently taking the Hare, but in following him, in all his Rings and Doubles, and thoſe that love plays, and ſuch Huntings, reſemble jealous men, who eagerly purſue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36427:31"/>what they apprehend to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, or as old age, which we all pray to attain, but fear to approach.</p>
            <p>But now I come to ſoar my diſcourſe to a much higher pitch, &amp; a more Elevated Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and to treat of the moſt noble part of man, the Soul, and of true Religion the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to Heavenly felicity, for without Holineſs, no man ſhall ſee the Lord; We muſt therefore now <hi>Madam,</hi> change the Scene of ſenſe for a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual one, and climb where earthly nature, can never fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us, to the pure and high Region of Heaven, which will inform us that the earlier diſcovering our plot of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36427:31"/>Heaven, will but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the play, and the more ſpeed, the better ſucceſs: for the joyes of Heaven are ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and admits of no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or diminution: not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike the divertiſements of Stage-playes, or Hunting, or any earthly delights, which cannot laſt, but for a ſeaſon, and decay in our very injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and muſt ſoon leave us, or we them; but Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts the more and longer we practice them, the better we ſhall like them; Heavenly joyes ſo far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all we can here leave, as they are all we can ever aſpire to have; this we all know, but few of us practice, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36427:32"/>we all love God, but few love to keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore now <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> tell you, as the Prologue to my inſuing diſcourſe, that the grand Plot, and whole deſign of it, moves chiefly on theſe two hinges, firſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming you, that the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is built on God's holy Word, the Scriptures; which we Proteſtants, eſteem to be a perfect Rule of Faith, and guide to our actions, and the true Touch-ſtone to try all matters by, that relate to the good of our Souls, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly containing in it, all things neceſſary to our ſalvation. The ſecond thing I chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36427:32"/>to prove, is, that neither the Pope, or the Popiſh Church are infallible; and theſe two ſhall make up the principal ſtories, in the little Model of this ſmall building. The pretended infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the grand perſwaſive Argument, and lure to invite men to it, and the ſtrongeſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Garriſon in all the Popes power; and all other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Perſwaſions, are but like the ſmall open Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages about this Garriſon, which muſt be ſervants to them, that are maſters of it; and if a Papiſt can be but once convinc'd, that neither the Pope, nor the Popiſh
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36427:33"/>Church are infallible, they will ſoon be brought to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and our remaining diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, will not be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable: I ſhall therefore one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lightly diſcourſe on them, and ſhall no further trouble you <hi>Madam,</hi> then briefly, to anſwer them in my own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I meet them, or as they follow me, and ſhall onely do as the <hi>Wolf</hi> do's when purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſnap, and bite in his own defence, againſt all oppoſers, without altering his pace, or changing his Road: I ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meddle with the Papiſts, but as I meet them in the way, or towards making of my way, to my two deſigned points, which are (as I ſaid
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36427:33"/>before,) to prove the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be a perfect Rule of Faith, and guide to our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and to anſwer, as I go, the Papiſts main Arguments and objections againſt it.</p>
            <p>Next, that 'tis againſt all Scripture, and reaſon, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, or the Popiſh Church ſhould be infallible; which is the main deſign of this diſcourſe, and if I can by God's aſſiſtance make but the Papiſts believe reaſon, (when againſt their own Church,) I doubt not but by this little Pigmie diſcourſe (as very dwarfiſh as 'tis,) not onely to hinder many tottering Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants from turning Papiſts, but to bring ſome ſtubborn
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36427:34"/>Papiſts to turn Proteſtants, or at leaſt not to have ſuch an infallible good opinion of their Church, and ſo damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a bad one of ours.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that this my diſcourſe ſhould be ended, as ſoon as your Patience; &amp; therefore all that I ſhall add either to the excuſing my ſelf, or juſtifying Mr. <hi>Chilingworth,</hi> is, that thus far of this diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my own writing, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, deſerves onely my Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and ſcarce your peruſal; but the following diſcourſe being extracted out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> deſerves your reading, but needs not any Apology.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:36427:34"/>
            <p>And becauſe I find the word Proteſtant is ſo badly, and over-largely interpreted; I ſhall firſt acquaint you, that we are not to underſtand by the word Proteſtant, the Doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Geneva</hi> or onely the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but that wherein they all agree with perfect Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; that the Bible is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Rule of our Faith, and guide to our Actions; and this (after having made the moſt diligent, and impartial ſearch of the true way to Eternal happineſs.) I fully believe, and that we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find any convincing ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:36427:35"/>but on this Rock of Gods word, the Bible, which I conceive to be the onely true Religion of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>If the Pope were indeed (what he unjuſtly ſayes he is, &amp; the Papiſts unreaſonably believe him to be,) an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble guide, then there needed no Bible, but if the Bible be, then there needs no Pope; for if I were to go a journey, and had a guide that could not err, what need I be taught the way, and having ſuch a guide, what need I apply my ſelf to another: So that in a word let us inform our ſelves the beſt we can, and conſider as much as we pleaſe, the more conſideration we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36427:35"/>take, the more confirmation we ſhall find, that there is no other foundation for a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Chriſtian to build an aſſured dependency on, than the Scriptures, for I am fully aſſur'd that God do's not; (and therefore man ought not to) require of any man more than this, to believe the Scripture to be the word of God, to uſe our beſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to find the true ſenſe of it, and to live, to our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt according to it.</p>
            <p>This I am ſure in reaſon we ought to believe a wiſer choice; Then if I ſhould guide my ſelf by the Roman Churches authority, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; when really they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36427:36"/>have nothing of certainty, but their uncertainty; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Pope againſt Pope, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils againſt Councils, ſome of their Fathers againſt others, and rather then fail ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, new Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions inrolled, and old ones Caſhiered, in a word one Church againſt another, and (if that be not enough) the Church of one age, againſt the Church of another; Whereas the Scripture being true and unalterable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all things neceſſary to our Salvation; I am ſecure, that by believing nothing elſe, I ſhall believe no falſhood in matter of Faith, &amp; if I miſtake the true ſenſe of Scripture,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36427:36"/>and ſo fall into error; yet I am ſecured from any dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous error, becauſe whilſt I am truly indeavouring to find the true ground of Scripture, I cannot but hold my error without obſtinacy, and be ready to forſake it, when a more probable and true ſenſe ſhall appear unto me: and then being aſſur'd, that all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary truths are plainly ſet down in Scripture; I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by believing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to believe all neceſſary truth, and he that do's ſo, if his life be anſwerable to his Faith, how is it poſſible he ſhould fail of Salvation.</p>
            <p>And though the Roman Church pretend to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36427:37"/>guide of Faith, and teacher of all Divine Truths; yet ſure that Title might much better, and more juſtly be given to the Scriptures, as their Teacher and Maſter.</p>
            <p>The Roman Church brags how ancient their Church is, but doubtleſs they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but the Scripture is more ancient, if they will but allow the Mother to be older than the Child.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts ſay their Church is a means of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians at unity, ſo are alſo the Scriptures, to thoſe that believe them in unity of belief, in matters neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts ſay their Church is Catholick, cetain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36427:37"/>the Scripture is more Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick; for all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the univerſal world do now, and ever did believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God, ſo much at leaſt, as to contain all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſalvation; whereas the Papiſts ſay, They onely are the true Church, and all other Chriſtians (though more than they) give them the lye for ſaying ſo.</p>
            <p>By following the Scriptures, I follow that whereby the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts prove their Churches In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; for were it not for Scripture, what pretence could the Papiſts have for it, or what true Notion could they receive of it; ſo that by
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36427:38"/>ſo doing, the Papiſts muſt plainly confeſs, That they themſelves are ſurer of the Truth of Scripture, than of their Churches Authority; for we muſt be ſurer of the proof, than of the thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or elſe 'tis no proof: ſo that following Scripture, I follow that which muſt be true, if the Papiſts Church be true; for their Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows it's truth; whereas if I follow the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I muſt follow that, which though the Scripture be true, may be falſe, nay more, muſt be falſe, if the Scripture be true; becauſe the Scripture is againſt it. Following the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Church, I muſt be a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36427:38"/>ſervant to my Saviour, and a ſubject to my King, onely at the pleaſure of the Pope, and renounce my Allegiance, when the Popes will is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him an Heretick; nay, I muſt believe vertue vice, and vice vertue, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for he both makes and unmakes Scripture as he thinks convenient; witneſs the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> which hath not paſt for Canonical, but of late years, in the Papiſts Church, who interpret Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture according to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but will not judge their Doctrine according to Scripture, for none like to weigh light Money in true ſcales. In ſhort, the Pope
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36427:39"/>adds, and leſſens, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets Divine Laws as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and they muſt ſtand for Laws, and be obeyed as ſuch; ſo that in effect he rules his people by his own Laws, and his own Laws by his own Lawyers, his Clergy, who dare not ſpeak nor uphold them, other than juſt ſuch as the Pope would have them; and indeed Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> gave the reaſon why more hold the Pope above the Councils, than the Councils above the Pope, becauſe the Pope gave Archbiſhopricks and Biſhopricks, but the Councils had none to give: and though the Papiſts ſay, his Holineſs cannot err, yet
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36427:39"/>let not the Papiſts forget what God ſayes in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, if (not onely the Pope) but if an Angel from Heaven ſhall preach any thing againſt the Goſpel of Chriſt, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>In following the Scripture we have God's expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and no colour of any prohibition, but to believe; the Popiſh Church infallible, we have no Scripture-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand at all, much leſs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs one.</p>
            <p>Following the Popiſh Church, we muſt believe many things, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove reaſon, but againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, witneſs Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas following the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36427:40"/>Scripture, we ſhall believe many miſeries, but no impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities; many things above our reaſon, but nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; Nay, we need not believe any thing, which reaſon will not convince us we ought to believe; for reaſon will convince any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chriſtian? that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is the Word of God, and there's no reaſon can be greater than this, that God ſays it, therefore it muſt be true.</p>
            <p>In a word, we Proteſtants believe, that all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to our ſalvation, are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently contain'd in Scripture, and what is not there evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contained, cannot be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36427:40"/>to be believed, and our reaſon is juſt and clear, becauſe nothing can challenge our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as to ſalvation, but what hath deſcended to us from our Bleſſed Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, by original and univerſal Tradition; now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Scripture hath thus deſcended to us, therefore nothing but Scripture can challenge our Belief.</p>
            <p>Now the grand difference between the Papiſts and us, concerning the Scripture, is this; We hold the Scripture to be the onely perfect Rule whereby to judge of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies. The Papiſts ſay, That they acknowledge the Scriptures to be a perfect
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36427:41"/>Rule, onely they deny that it excluded unwritten Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which in effect is this; they ſay, 'Tis as perfect a Rule, as a Writing can be, onely they deny it to be as perfect a Rule as a Writing may be; either they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke their acknowledgment, or retract their contradiction of it, for both cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſtand together: for if they will but ſtand to what they have granted, that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is as perfect a Rule of Faith, as a Writing can be, they muſt then grant it ſo compleat, as it needs no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and ſo evident, that it needs no interpretation, for both theſe properties are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36427:41"/>to a perfect Rule: and that a writing is capable of both theſe properties, and perfections, is moſt plain, for he that denies it, muſt ſay that ſomething may be ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en which cannot be written, for if ſuch a compleat evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent rule of Faith, may be delivered by word of mouth, as the Papiſts pretend may, and is, and whatſoever is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by word of mouth, may alſo be written; then ſuch a compleat and evident rule of Faith, may alſo be written, for the Argument is moſt plain, whatſoever may be ſpoken may be written; a perfect rule of Faith has been ſpoken, therefore a perfect
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36427:42"/>rule of Faith may be written; If the Papiſts cannot ſee this plain concluſion, they had beſt deſire more light to be added to the Sun:</p>
            <p>The Papiſt pretend their Church to be, the infallible Teacher of all Divine Truths, and an infallible interpreter of all obſcurities in the Faith, but the Papiſts will, I hope, give us leave to admire, how they can pretend to Teach them in all places, without writing them down, that is certainly, beyond the reach of their power to do, as well as our belief that 'tis to be done.</p>
            <p>And for the Papiſts ſaying there muſt be a living autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36427:42"/>beſide the Scripture, or elſe controverſies cannot be ended; Proteſtants anſwer; neceſſary controverſies, are and may be decided, and if they be not, 'tis not the defect of the rule in Scripture, but the default of men; ſo that if neceſſary controverſies be ended, 'tis no matter if the unneceſſary be not; for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs if God had required it, he would alſo have provided ſome means to effect it; but ſure it does not ſtand with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſon it ſhould be the Pope, becauſe he cannot be a Judge, being a partie; indeed in civil controverſies, a Judge without being a partie may end them, but in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36427:43"/>of Religion, a Judge of neceſſity muſt be a concerned partie, and I am ſure the Pope to us is the chief, and moſt concerned partie, being really concerned as much as his Popedom is worth.</p>
            <p>Now we Proteſtants make the Papiſts this plain anſwer, that the means of agreeing differences, muſt neceſſarily be, either by the appointment of God, or men; men ſure it cannot be, for then ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal wiſe Proteſtants, may doe, as well as Papiſts, for let the Papiſts ſhew us if they can where God hath appointed that the Pope alone, or any confirm'd by the Pope, or that Society of Chriſtians,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:36427:43"/>which adhere to him, ſhall be the infallible Judge of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; we deſire the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, if they can to let us ſee any of thoſe aſſertions, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet down in Scripture, as in all reaſon a thing of this nature ought to be, or at leaſt delivered with a full conſent of Fathers, nay let them ſo much as ſhew us where 'tis in plain tearms, taught by any one Father, in Four hundred years after our bleſſed Saviour Chriſt; and if the Papiſts cannot do this, as we believe they cannot; where I pray is their either Scripture or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the Pope or his Councils ſhould obtrude themſelves as Judges over us Proteſtants.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:36427:44"/>
            <p>Next we would deſire to know from the Papiſts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do certainly know or not, the ſence of thoſe Scriptures, by which they are led to the knowledge of their Church, for if they do not, how come they to know their Church is infallible; but if they do, then ſure they ought to give us leave to have the ſame means and ability to know other plain places in Scripture, which they have to know theirs; for if all Scriptures be obſcure, how come they to know the ſenſe of thoſe places; but if ſome place of it be plain, why pray may not Proteſtants under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them as well as Papiſts.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:36427:44"/>
            <p>The Papiſts ſay, That the Scriptures are in themſelves true and infallible, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the direction of the Church, we have no certain means to know, which Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations be faithful and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, or what is the true meaning of Scriptures; and this is the common Argument and general Relief of all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: To which the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants anſwer, That yet all theſe things muſt firſt be known, before we can know the directions of their Church to be infallible; for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts cannot pretend any other proof of it, but onely ſome Texts of Canonical Scripture, truly interpreted; therefore
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36427:45"/>either they muſt be miſtaken in thinking there is no other means to know theſe things, but their Churches infallible direction, or elſe we muſt be excluded from all means of knowing her directions to be infallible; for the proof muſt be ſurer than the thing to be proved, or 'tis no proof; And upon better conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I am confident the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts dare not deny, but that 'tis moſt certain, Faith hath been given by other means than the Church; for ſure they will not ſay, that <hi>Adam</hi> received Faith by the Church, nor <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Job,</hi> who received Faith by Revelation; and alſo the Holy Apoſtles,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36427:45"/>who received Faith by the miracles, and preaching of our Bleſſed Saviour: ſo that you ſee, and they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but their general Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is contradictory; and to make it yet plainer, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know of the Papiſts, if they ſhould meet with a man, that believed neither Scripture, Church, nor God, but declares he is both ready, and willing to believe them all, if the Papiſt can ſhew him ſufficient grounds to build his Faith upon, will the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt tell ſuch a man, there are no certain grounds how he may be converted to their Church; or there are; if the Papiſts ſay there are none,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36427:46"/>they make Religion an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thing: but if they ſay there are, then they muſt neceſſarily either argue wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-like, that their Church is infallible, becauſe it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, or elſe ſhew there are other certain grounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſaying, the Church is infallible, to prove its infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts demand of the Proteſtants, if they believe the Apoſtles wrote all the Scriptures, for if they did not, how come we to call and believe them Apoſtolical, and not the Writings of thoſe that writ them: To which we anſwer; Though all the Scriptures were not written
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:36427:46"/>by the Apoſtles themſelves, yet they were all confirm'd by them; and though a Clerk writes a Statute, and the King, Lords and Commons confirm it in Parliament; I believe they would eſteem it very improper to call it the Statute of ſuch a Clerk, though writ by him, but an Act of Parliament, becauſe it was confirm'd by all their conſents, and ſo becomes their Act, not the Clerks.</p>
            <p>The Papiſt deſires us to tell them in what Language the Scriptures remained uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and we deſire them, to ſatisfie us whether it be neceſſary to know it, or not neceſſary, if it be not, I hope
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36427:47"/>we may do well without it, but if it be neceſſary we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire firſt, that they will pleaſe to tell us what became of their Church for One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand five hundred years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all which time they muſt confeſs, they had no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Scripture; till the time that Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth, ſet forth their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Edition of the vulgar Tranſlation, and none ſure can have the confidence to deny, but that there was great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Copies currant in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of their Church, and read ſo, which Copies might be falſe in ſome things, but more than one ſort of them could not poſſibly be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36427:47"/>true in all things. And Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> his Bible dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd from Pope <hi>Clement</hi> his Bible, in a multitude of places, which makes us deſire to be ſatisfied of the Papiſts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> his time, their Church had any defined Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of Scriptures or not, for if they had not, then 'tis moſt evident that their Church was a moſt excellent keeper of Scripture, for fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years together, that had not all that time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd, what was Scripture, and what was not, but if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ſay they had, then we demand, was that ſet forth by Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> or was
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:36427:48"/>it ſet forth by Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> or if by a third different from them both, why do they not name him; if it were that ſet forth by Pope <hi>Sixtus,</hi> then 'tis now condemn'd by Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> if that of <hi>Clement,</hi> 'twas condemned by that of <hi>Sixtus,</hi> ſo that error muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be betwixt them, let them chuſe which ſide they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And for the book of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees,</hi> I hope they will allow it defin'd Canonical, before St. <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s time, though he would not allow it Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, but onely for the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Church.</p>
            <p>We further deſire to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of the Papiſts, if the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36427:48"/>book of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedom,</hi> and the Epiſtle to St. <hi>James,</hi> were by the holy Apoſtles approved Canonical, or not, if they were appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Apoſtles Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, ſure the Papiſts cannot deny, but they had a ſufficient definition and authority, not to queſtion them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore err'd in doing ſo. And if they were not approved Canonical by the Apoſtles, with what impudence dare the Roman Church now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them as Canonical, and yet pretend that all their Doctrine is Apoſtolical, and if they ſay theſe books were not queſtioned, they ſhould do well to tell which books
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36427:49"/>they mean, which were not alwayes known to be Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, but have afterward been received by the Roman Church to be ſuch, ſo that this argument reaches theſe, as wel as theſe.</p>
            <p>And further we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that there is not the ſame reaſons, for the Churches abſolute infallibility, as for the Apoſtles, and Scriptures, for if the Church falls into an error, it may be reformed by comparing it with the Rules of the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in Scripture, but if the Apoſtles have err'd in delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Doctrine of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Scripture, then the Roman Church cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36427:49"/>for Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Canonical Writers, are the foundation of the Church, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes 'tis built upon the foundation of Apoſtles and Prophets.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude this part of my diſcourſe in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few words, let the Papiſts anſwer, if they can but theſe five words. All Scripture is Divinely inſpired. Let them ſhew us ſo much for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, and ſhew us if they can, where 'tis written in Scripture, that all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Popiſh Church are Divinely inſpired, and all our Controverſies will be at an end, but I believe they can
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36427:50"/>ever do that, without ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tranſubſtantiation mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of words.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts deſire us to ſhew them an exact Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of our fundamentals, to which we anſwer. That God may be ſufficiently known to one, and not ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to an ether, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that may be funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, and neceſſary to one, which is not to another; which variety of circumſtances ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it impoſſible to ſet down an exact Catalogue of funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, for God requires more of them to whom he gives more, and leſs of thoſe to whom he gives leſs, more of a Commander of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36427:50"/>than a poor ſimple Turn ſpit. 'Tis a plain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of God to us Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that the Sacrament the Euchariſt ſhould be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in both kinds, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11 <hi>c.</hi> 28 <hi>v.</hi> And that the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Hymns and Prayers of the Church, ſhould be in ſuch a Language as is moſt for Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14, and 15, 16. yet the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not ſeeing this, by reaſon of the vail, would be very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, if we told them 'twould prejudice their ſuppoſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility.</p>
            <p>We read in St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> that the Goſpel was to be preacht to all Nations, and this was a truth revealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36427:51"/>our Saviours Aſcention, yet if the Church had been aſked, before the converſion of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> they would have certainly told you, it had not been neceſſary to teach all Nations; for 'tis moſt apparent out of the 11th of the <hi>Acts,</hi> they all believed ſo, until St. <hi>Peter</hi> was better informed by a viſion from Heaven, and the converſion of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and then they turn'd quite of a differing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and eſteemed it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to teach all Nations, and yet were ſtill a Church: The Papiſts are pleaſed to ſay, the Proteſtants differ in Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, which indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to us very irrational;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36427:51"/>for if they ſay, We Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants differ in Fundamentals, how then can they ſay, We are members of the ſame Church, one with another, more than they are with ours, or ours with theirs; and why do they object our difference more with one another, than with themſelves; and if we do not differ in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, why do they upbraid us, with Fundamental diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences amongſt our ſelves. We believe the Catholick Church cannot periſh, yet we believe ſhe may and did err, as I prov'd juſt before: but thus much we Proteſtants declare in general, that we eſteem it ſufficient for any
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36427:52"/>mans ſalvation to believe Gods Word, the Scripture, and that it contains all things neceſſary to our ſalvation, and that we do our utmoſt endeavours to find, believe, and follow the true ſenſe of it; and being we are ſure, that all that is any way neceſſary is there, believing all that is there, we are ſure we believe all that is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And therefore 'tis but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to ſay, that any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon, who truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the Scriptures, and heartily endeavours to know the Will of God, and to do it, is as ſecure, nay ſecurer from the danger of erring in Fundamentals, than the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:36427:52"/>Church: for 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible any man ſo qualified, ſhould fall into an errour, that can prove damnable to him; for God requires no more of any man to his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely his true and beſt endeavours to be ſaved: And for the Papiſts Sacrament of Confeſſion, which they hold is ſo abſolute and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and ſo much upbraid us for the want of it, we anſwer, We know no ſuch abſolute neceſſity of it; but yet we hold, we muſt not onely confeſs our ſins, but forſake them, or we ſhall not find mercy: And we Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants farther believe, that they that confeſs their ſins,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:36427:53"/>ſhall find mercy, though they onely confeſs them to God, and not to man: And more, that they who confeſs them both to God and man, and do not in time forſake them, ſhall not find mercy.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the Papiſts Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Repentance for Remiſſion of ſins, though we Proteſtants know no ſuch; yet we allow, and obſerve the ſame Duty, but publick before the Church, which was the conſtant practice of the primitive Church; and <hi>Rhemanus</hi> himſelf, though ſo great a Champion for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, writes, That the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion then uſed, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church; and that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36427:53"/>
               <hi>Auricular</hi> confeſſion was not hen in the World.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts will tell you that our Biſhops have not the true power of Ordination, but that has been ſo clearly anſwered, and ſo truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at large by ſo many al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, as I ſhall not need here ſo much as to name it: onely let me in a word, remember the Papiſts, that they cannot well deny, but that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts themſelves whom the Papiſts eſteemed as bad as us, as being Hereticks, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks; yet St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Optatus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did both acknowledge that they had the ſame Baptiſm, Creed, and Sacrament, and that theſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:36427:54"/>Donatiſt, Fathers, though Schiſmaticks, and Hereticks, gave true Ordination, or elſe ſome of theſe were not then eſteemed Sacraments; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them take which they pleaſe, there muſt be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of one ſide.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts pretend they have an unanſwerable objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Proteſtants, which is, That we have diſcords in matters of Faith, without, any means of agreement: to which we anſwer, that the Scripture does not let us want ſolid means of agreement in matters neceſſary to ſalvation, and for our agreement in all controverſies of Religion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they muſt ſay we have
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36427:54"/>means to agree about them, or we have not; if they ſay we have; why did they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deny it, if they ſay we have no means, why are they ſo unjuſt to find fault with us for not agreeing; when they themſelves, ſay we have no means to agree.</p>
            <p>But for a Plaiſter to this ſoar, they are ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry civil, as to tell us, we may come to their Church: and they agree in matters of faith, but the plain truth of it is, that they define all matters of faith, to be thoſe wherein they agree; ſo that to ſay the Roman Church does agree in matters of Faith, is but to ſay, they agree in thoſe things,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:36427:55"/>they do agree in, and ſure they cannot deny, but we Proteſtants do the ſame.</p>
            <p>But we muſt deſire the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to give us leave to tell them, that they moſt grosly miſtake, if they ſay, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in matters of Faith, as for proof; ſome of them hold it againſt Faith, to take the Oath of Allegiance, others 'tis againſt Faith to refuſe that Oath.</p>
            <p>Some hold it of Faith, that the Pope (is head of the Church by Divine Law: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the contrary, ſome hold it of Faith that the bleſſed Virgin was free from actual ſin, others the contrary; ſome that the Popes power over
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36427:55"/>Princes in Temporalities is <hi>de fide,</hi> others the contrary: ſome that 'tis univerſal Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceived in actual ſin, others the contrary; And how the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Franci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcans,</hi> and other Orders differ to this day; I am ſure needs no <hi>memorandum;</hi> and the beſt Jeaſt of all is, the Papiſts have not ſo much as yet agreed in their very pretended means of agreement, and yet have the confidence to pretend an Unity more than the Proteſtants; ſor ſome of them ſay, the Pope with a Council may determine all Controverſies, others deny it: Some hold, That a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36427:56"/>Council, without a Pope, may do ſo, others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this: Others ſay, Both in conjunction are infallible Determiners, others deny this: And ſome among the Papiſts hold, The acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on of the Decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils by the Univerſal Church, is the onely way to decide Controverſies, which others deny by denying their Church to be infallible; and yet every part, pretends to be part of the Church.</p>
            <p>In a word, can the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts deny, but that there has been Popes, againſt Popes, Councils againſt Councils; Nay, Councils confirmed by Popes, againſt Popes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:36427:56"/>by Councils. And Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Church of ſome Ages, againſt the Church of other Ages; and ſince every part of the Body is ſo out of order, methinks they ſhould not brag of ſo perfect a health as they do.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts ſay (and do but ſay it) that their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is held Catholick; and therefore they eſteem it an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent madneſs of us Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to diſpute againſt the practice of the whole Church; Firſt, That their Doctrine is Catholick, we anſwer; That the greateſt number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the world deny it; ſo that they cannot truly ſay, we diſpute againſt the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:36427:57"/>of the whole Church; And farther we ſay, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing we ſhould in complement to them grant, that their Church is Catholick and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal; yet we ſay, That is no ſufficient proof, it came originally from the Apoſtles, witneſs the Doctrine of the <hi>Milenaries,</hi> and the neceſſity of the Euchariſt for Infants, which was generally taught by the Univerſal Church, and believed as Apoſtolical Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but yet contradicted by the Univerſal Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards: This, I am ſure, the Papiſts dare not deny; ſo that we unavoidably caſt the Papiſts upon this Rock, that they muſt either conclude
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:36427:57"/>the Apoſtles were Fountains of contradictorie Doctrines; or that the Univerſal Doctrine of the preſent Church is no ſufficient proof, that it came originally from the Apoſtles, becauſe from Church Univerſal of one time, and the Church Univerſal of another time did differ.</p>
            <p>Next for their ſaying, 'tis inſolent madneſs to diſpute againſt the practice of the whole Church, Firſt we are ſure, we can bring more Chriſtian witneſſes, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they are the whole Church, than they can bring to prove it: but ſuppoſing we were as mad as they ſay we are, and would have us to be, to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:36427:58"/>diſpute againſt the whole practice of the Church; yet I hope we may deſire to know of the Papiſts if they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but that 'twas the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, of the whole Church in St. <hi>Au'ſtine</hi>'s time, and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then an Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition even by St. <hi>Au'ſtine</hi> himſelf, that the Euchariſt ſhould be adminiſtred to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; And then let them tell us, Whether it be inſolent madneſs to diſpute againſt the practice of the whole Church, or is it not; if it be not, why do they accuſe us for it; but if it be inſolent madneſs, how mad and inſolent is the Papiſt Church, not onely to diſpute againſt this practice of the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:36427:58"/>Univerſal Church, of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Euchariſt to Infants, but utterly aboliſhing the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it.</p>
            <p>So that the very worſt the Papiſts can ſay of us, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ſay to be true, is that we but do, what they themſelves own already to have done.</p>
            <p>And though the Papiſts are pleaſed to ſay that the Holy Scriptures, and ancient Fathers, aſſign ſeparation from the viſible Church, as a mark of Hereſie, yet they cannot ſhew one plain Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to confirm it.</p>
            <p>And for the Papiſts brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Antiquity and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of their Churches
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36427:59"/>Doctrine, (though we allow it very ancient, (bating the primative times) we anſwer firſt as to its Antiquity, we deſire to ſee what Antiquity they can ſhew for their giving the Communion but in one kind, when they know that the Adminiſtring it in both kinds, was the practice of the Church for a Thouſand years after Chriſt; what Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the lawfulneſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency of the Latine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for the preſent uſe of indulgences; For the Popes power in Temporalities over Princes; for the Picturing the Trinity; For the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of worſhipping Pictures and Images; Fox their Beads;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36427:59"/>For their whole worſhip of the bleſſed Virgin; For their Oblations, in the notion of Sacrifices to her, and other Saints; For their ſaying <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> and <hi>Creeds</hi> to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of them, and <hi>Ave Maries</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> For the infallibility of the Biſhop, or Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> For their Doctrine of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins immunity from actual ſin; For the neceſſity of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular Confeſſion; For the neceſſity of the Prieſts inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obtain benefit by any of their Sacraments. And laſtly for their licentious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in holding, that though a man lives and dies without the practiſe of any Chriſtian
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36427:60"/>vertue, and with the Habits of many damnable ſins un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified; yet if at the laſt moment of his life, he has any ſorrow for his ſins, and joyn confeſſion to it, he ſhall certainly be ſaved; This is a Doctrine may keep many ſouls out of Heaven, but I doubt will ſcarce carry any one there. So that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Doctrine being ancient, is nothing, as long as 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that they hold many dangerous errors, as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the <hi>Milenaries,</hi> and the <hi>Communicating Infants</hi> was more ancient, than their Doctrine, and 'tis plain that antiquity, unleſs it be abſolute and primative, is not a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36427:60"/>ſign of true Doctrine: And the very Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, aſſure us that in their dayes, the myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was working.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts demand how comes it to paſs that their Doctrine is ſo univerſal, (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting that weeds ſpread faſter than good herbs:) And we ask them how the errors of the <hi>Milenaries,</hi> and the <hi>Communicating Infants</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo univerſal, let them tell us this, and we will tell them that, for what is done in ſome, may be done in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts ask us where our Church was before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and tell us, becauſe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36427:61"/>t'was no Church before him, therefore it can be no true Church at all. To which we anſwer, that this cauſe is no cauſe; For though <hi>Luther</hi> had no being before <hi>Luther,</hi> yet none can deny, but that he was, when he was, though he could not be before he was; So there may be a true Church after <hi>Luther,</hi> though there was none for ſome ages before him: as ſince <hi>Columbus</hi> his time there have been Chriſtians in <hi>America,</hi> though there were none for many Ages before: for it does not follow, that nothing but a Church can poſſibly get a Church, nor that the preſent being of a true Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36427:61"/>neceſſarily upon the perpetuity of a Church in all Ages; for though I cannot deny the Churches perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet that's not here neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our difference; but that a falſe Church (by Gods providence over ruling it) may preſerve a means of confuting their own Hereſies, and ſo reduce men to truth, and raiſe a true Church, (I mean the integrity of the word of God with men.) Thus the Jewes preſerve means to make men Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Papiſts preſerve means to make men Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and the Proteſtants falſe Church, (as the Romans call it,) preſerves men Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts:
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36427:62"/>nor does it appear that the perpetuity of the Church, is the truth of the Papiſts Church, for they ſpeak, as if they were the onely Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the World before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> when the whole World knowes, that this is but talk, and that there were other Chriſtians beſides the Papiſts that might have perpetuated the Church, though there had not been then one Papiſt in being: for ſure there was a Catholick Church before the Roman one. Next the Papiſt ſay, to hold that the viſible Church is not perpetual, is a Hereſie, ſo that <hi>Luthers</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation being but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and not univerſal, nor but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36427:62"/>of late date, it can have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with the viſible and perpetual Church; which the Proteſtants anſwer thus: To ſay the viſible Church is not perpetual, is properly a Hereſie, but the Papiſts cannot deny, but that the Apoſtles who preach'd the Goſpel in the beginn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, did believe the Church univerſal, though their preaching at the beginning was not ſo: So <hi>Luther</hi> alſo might well believe the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, though his Reformation was but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the Church in the Apoſtles time being univerſal <hi>de jure</hi> of right, but not <hi>de facto</hi> in fact.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:36427:63"/>
            <p>Nor did <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers (as the Papiſt are pleaſed to miſ-cal many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants) forſake the whole Church, but the corruptions of it, in renouncing ſome of their corrupt practices, and this the Proteſtants ſay they did without Schiſm, becauſe they had cauſe to do it, and no man can have cauſe to be a Schiſmatick, becauſe he is onely one who leaves the Church without a cauſe; for 'tis not onely ſeperation, but a cauſeleſs ſeperation from the Church, that is Schiſmatical: and I think t'will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, before I go any farther, to diſtinguiſh the difference between Hereſie, and Schiſm.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36427:63"/>
               <hi>Hereſie is anobſtinate defence of any error againſt any neceſſary Article of the Chriſtian Faith. Schiſm is a cauſeleſs ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one part of the Church from another.</hi> Now we Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſay ſtill, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſook the whole Church, or the external Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of it, but onely that part of it which is corrupted, and is to be fear'd will ſtill continue ſo; viz. <hi>The Papiſt Church;</hi> and forſook not, but onely reformed an other part, which part they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were: and ſure the Papiſts will not ſay, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants forſook themſelves, nor their own Communion: and therefore the Papiſts ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36427:64"/>muſt be a very weak in urging, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants joyned themſelves to no other part of the Church, therefore they muſt ſeparate from the whole Church; which the Proteſtants ſay is a falſe concluſion, in as much as they themſelves were part of it, and ſtill continue ſo; and therefore the Proteſtants could no more ſeparate from the whole, then from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>So that by the Rule of Reaſon, if Proteſtants be Schiſmaticks, becauſe they differ from one part of the viſible Church, by the ſame reaſon the Proteſtants may ſay that the Roman Church
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36427:64"/>is in a manner made up of Schiſmaticks, for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are Schiſmaticks from the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> from the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> from the <hi>Canoniſts:</hi> the <hi>Franſciſcans</hi> from the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> from the <hi>Franſciſcans;</hi> for all theſe (as the World knowes) differ in point of Doctrine, and betwixt them there is an irreconcileable contradiction; and therefore one part muſt be in error. And if the Papiſts will but ſtand to juſtifie what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare as truth, <hi>that every error againſt a revealed truth is a Hereſie,</hi> they holding for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as a revealed truth, the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36427:65"/>immaculate conception of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> then conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Dominicans</hi> that hold and declare it an error in Doctrine, muſt neceſſarily hold a Hereſie; Now it may be a fault to be in error, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it many times proceeds from a fault; but ſure Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants forſaking error, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a ſin, unleſs to be in error, be a vertue: ſo hardly do Papiſts deal with us Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, as they will either damn us in making us follow their falſe opinions, or elſe brand us as Schiſmaticks for leaving them.</p>
            <p>And yet the rational ſort of <hi>Papiſts</hi> can hardly deny, but the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:36427:65"/>muſt be a ſafer <hi>Religion</hi> than theirs, in <hi>worſhipping Pictures,</hi> in <hi>Invocating Saints,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels;</hi> in <hi>denying the Lay-men</hi> the <hi>Communion in both kinds,</hi> as was commanded by our <hi>bleſſed Saviour; in celebrating</hi> their <hi>Church Service in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Tongue,</hi> which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by St. <hi>Paul. in ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sacrament;</hi> and in <hi>all theſe</hi> a rational Papiſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, but he is on the more dangerous ſide, as to the committing of ſin, and the Proteſtant in the more ſecure way as to the avoiding it. For in all theſe things, if <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſay true, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do that which is impious; but on the other ſide, if the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:36427:66"/>were in the right, yet the Proteſtants might be ſecure enough too; for their fault would be onely this, that they ſhould onely, not do ſome things which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſs is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary to be done.</p>
            <p>And truly the Proteſtants are ſo charitably civil, as on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſay of Papiſts, as St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> did of the <hi>Donatiſts, That Catholicks approved the Doctrine of the</hi> Donatiſts, <hi>but abhorred their Hereſie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptization.</hi> So <hi>Proteſtants</hi> approve the Fundamental and neceſſary Truths which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> retain, by which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good ſouls among them may be ſaved, but abhor the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:36427:66"/>many ſuperſtitions they uſe in their Religion. And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing theſe errours of the <hi>Popiſh Church</hi> were in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not damnable, to them that believe as they profeſs; yet for us <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs what we do not believe, and eſteem thoſe as Divine Truths, which we believe not to be either Divine or true; would be doubtleſs damnable as to us: for 'tis certain, Two men may do the ſame thing, and it may be ſinful to one, and not to the other: as ſuppoſe a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried woman gives her ſelf out to be a widow, and one know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Huſband to be alive, marries her, doubtleſs his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36427:67"/>of her was adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; but a ſecond man comes, and after ſeeing her pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Huſband buried, marries her, and dies without the leaſt information, of her Firſt Huſbands being then alive, his ignorance ſure protected him from ſin, and the ſecond Huſbands knowledge of the ſin he acted, condemned him of Adultery; and though his fault might be palliated with ſome excuſes, yet it can never be defended by any juſt Apology: And ſo though we read in Scripture, that it was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that meat offered to Idols might lawfully be eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; yet he ſays, it any ſhould
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36427:67"/>eat it with a doubtful conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he ſhould ſin, and be condemned for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſing we Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ought not to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the Papiſts Church, for ſin, and errours, if ſhe had not enjoyn'd and impoſed them on us; yet ſince ſhe does maintain them with ſuch obſtinacy, and impoſes them with ſuch Tyranny, we ought certainly to ſay with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>John, 'Tis better to forſake men than God;</hi> and leave the Popiſh Church communion, rather than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or profeſs known errours as Divine Truths; for as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> tells us, that to ſay <hi>The Lord hath ſaid ſo,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:36427:68"/>when the Lord hath not ſaid ſo,</hi> is a high preſumption, and great ſin, be the matter never ſo ſmall; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Virgins abſtaining from marriage, he ſaid, <hi>He had no commandment of the Lord, but I declare my own judgement of it.</hi> Now if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had given this as God's command, ſurely we might have juſtly contradicted him, and made a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween divine Revelation, and humane Judgement.</p>
            <p>So that for a Proteſtant to abide in the Communion of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> is ſo far from ſecuring him from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as that if <hi>I,</hi> or any
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:36427:68"/>
               <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſhould continue in it, I am confident I could not be ſaved by it, and the reaſon is, becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will not admit of my commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, without profeſſing the entire Popiſh Doctrine to be true; and profeſs this I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but I muſt perpetually exulcerate my conſcience: and though the errours of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church were not in themſelves damnable, yet for me to reſiſt known Truths, and to continue in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of known Errours and Falſhoods, is certainly a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital ſin, and of great affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the ſin which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgiven.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if the errours of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36427:69"/>the <hi>Roman</hi> Church did not warrant our departure, yet the tyrannous impoſition of them would be our ſufficient juſtification; for they force us either to forſake the <hi>Papiſts Communion,</hi> or profeſs as <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel truths,</hi> what our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aſſures us is very little a kin to them: ſo that the Proteſtants were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to forſake thoſe errours of the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> and not the <hi>Church,</hi> but the errours, and we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> did, and do ſtill continue members of the <hi>Church,</hi> having onely left what appear'd moſt plain to us, to be <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious.</hi> And we ſeparate no more from the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:36427:69"/>than ſhe has ſeparated from the <hi>Ancient Church;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; to ſpeak properly, our difference is more againſt the <hi>Court,</hi> than <hi>Church of</hi> Rome, which has introduced ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new ceremonies and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices in the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> as was never heard, nor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the primitive Times; as for one inſtance of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, I might give you; <hi>Their denying the cup to the Laity,</hi> which was never pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the Church a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years after our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> brag ſo much of, and depend ſo entirely on, the <hi>infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of their Church, I ſhall
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36427:70"/>paſs by their Out-works, and ſearch a little into this their Grand Fort, the <hi>infallibility</hi> of their Church; for except they prove that, they prove nothing; but in proving that they prove all; and if the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> could ſatisfie me either by <hi>Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that their <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>infallible,</hi> I ſhould not onely be of their <hi>Church</hi> to morrow, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent I was not ſooner; but really by all that I ever heard or read, for their making it good; I find cauſe onely to admire their confidence, but not at all to eſteem their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>The chief Method they take, and degrees they uſe,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36427:70"/>to prove the <hi>infallibility</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> are by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale theſe. Firſt, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was Head and chief amongſt the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that there was given to him and his ſucceſſors by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Univerſal Authority over his Militant <hi>Church;</hi> That the Pope or Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is St. <hi>peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, and has his Authority of Univerſal Biſhop, and conſequently the <hi>Roman Church</hi> being built upon this <hi>Rock, is infallible,</hi> all which I doubt not, but to prove, to be inconſiſtent with, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory both to <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt point of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s being Head of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:36427:71"/>which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> all ſtile him, and ſay he was called from thence <hi>Cephas,</hi> which is derived from the <hi>Greek<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> word Head, it is a moſt groſs miſtake; for <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> is a <hi>Syriack</hi> word that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifies <hi>Stone;</hi> but this is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the by: Now we <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſay, though we allow St. <hi>Peter</hi> might have primacy of Order; yet we cannot grant he had ſupremacy of power over the other <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> for ſure it cannot ſtand with the leaſt reaſon, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould have authority over all the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and yet never act the leaſt authority ever any one of them.</p>
            <p>Nor is it reaſonable to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36427:71"/>believe, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> having authority over all the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> for about 25 years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould never ſhew the leaſt power over any of them all that time, nor ſo much as receive the leaſt ſubjection from them; ſure any one muſt think this as ſtrange, and un reaſonable, as if a King of <hi>England</hi> for 25 years together ſhould not do one Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality among his ſubjects, nor receive any one acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from them.</p>
            <p>Nor ſure is it leſs ſtrange and unreaſonable, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould ſo many Ages after, know this ſo certainly, as they pretend they do, and yet that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:36427:72"/>after that theſe words were ſpoke in their hearing by vertue whereof St. <hi>Peter</hi> is pretended to be made their head, ſhould ſtill be ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it, as to queſtion our <hi>Saviour, which of them ſhould be the greateſt,</hi> by which ſure we may rationally conclude, they did not then know; for if they did, their queſtion had been needleſs, and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in deſiring to be taught, what they already knew.</p>
            <p>And what yet appears more ſtrange then all, is that our Saviour ſhould not have helped them out of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror by telling them St. <hi>Peter</hi> was the man, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them in the contrary
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36427:72"/>by ſaying <hi>the Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, but it ſhould not be ſo among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again it is as ſtrange and unreaſonable, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſo farr forget both St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and himſelf, as in mentioning ſo often St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he ſhould ſtill do it without aſcribing him any title of honour: Nor does it ſtand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>with reaſon, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the ſeveral degrees of men in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould omit giving St. <hi>Peter</hi> the higheſt, if it had been his due; but place him in the ſame rank and Equipage with the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes <hi>God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:36427:73"/>(not firſt St. <hi>Peter</hi> then the reſt of the Apoſtles) but <hi>firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> now certainly if <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> were all firſt, that is all equal, how could one be in greater power than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, though we ſhould grant againſt all theſe probabilities, and many more, that <hi>Optatus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> meant that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was head of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> yet ſure the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ſtill very farr from proving, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was to be ſo at all, much leſs by divine right, ſucceſſor to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his headſhip and <hi>Authority.</hi> For what incongruity is there, if
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:36427:73"/>we ſay, that <hi>Optatus</hi> might ſucceed St. <hi>Peter</hi> as his heir and ſucceſſor, in that part of his Government of that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> (as ſure he did even whilſt St. <hi>Peter</hi> was living) and yet that neither he, nor any man was to ſucceed him in his Apoſtleſhip, nor in the Government of the Church univerſal: as though a Biſhop ſhould leave his Son heir to all he dyed poſſeſſed of, I hope you will not conclude, therefore he muſt neceſſarily ſucceed him in the Biſhoprick he dyed ſeized of. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were men all called, and divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which was the immediate
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36427:74"/>gift of <hi>God,</hi> and therefore could not be left as a Legacy by man; for though it be in any mans power to leave his Eſtate, yet 'tis in no mans power to leave to his Son, his acquir'd parts at his death. 'Tis further worth your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, and ſpecial notice, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf and the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foundation of the <hi>Church,</hi> were to be themſelves the foundation of it, and are accordingly ſo called in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> And therefore as in a building 'tis incongruous that foundations, ſhould ſucceed foundations, ſo it may be in the <hi>Church,</hi> that Apoſtles ſhould ſucceed <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:36427:74"/>Church being built upon <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor indeed does the grand argument of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for their <hi>Pope,</hi> extend any further in Reallity then to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> for thus goes their main argument. St. <hi>Peter</hi> was firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> did not then attribute to themſelves, each one his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Chair</hi> (underſtand in that City of <hi>Rome,</hi> for in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, others had <hi>Chairs</hi> beſides St. <hi>Peter</hi>) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayes the Papiſt, he is a Schiſmatick who againſt that one ſingle <hi>Chair</hi> erects ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: (underſtand ſtill in the ſame place) and this is the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:36427:75"/>ground &amp; the Authority the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, the <hi>Pope</hi> has to be Succeſſor to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to exerciſe Authority over the Univerſal <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſure the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> urge more rationally in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, That St. <hi>Peter</hi> wrote <hi>Two Catholick Epiſtles,</hi> in which he mentions his own departure, and writes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the <hi>faith:</hi> but yet in neither of theſe <hi>Two Epiſtles</hi> does he commend the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to the guidance and authority of his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Succeſſor</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> which ſure if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had intended, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have forgot to have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it.</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:36427:75"/>
            <p>And ſince the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and adore the <hi>Popes</hi> power, let us <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo admire his way and means of attaining this power; for though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, that aſſoon as he is made <hi>Pope,</hi> he has his authority immediately from <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet at the very ſame time the <hi>Papiſts</hi> all know, that he cannot be made <hi>Pope,</hi> but by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Election of the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals;</hi> ſo that I am ſure by the very ſame reaſon, any man that is choſen a Magiſtrate in any Town under the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Territories, may claim his Authority as immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as well as the <hi>Pope.</hi> And further, that the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:36427:76"/>proving his being made <hi>Pope,</hi> does not render him infallible, I could give a hundred inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of the Hiſtory of <hi>Popes,</hi> but that will not ſuit well with my deſigned brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but let's aſk the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> if <hi>Liberius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> after Two years Baniſhment, did not by the ſollicitation of <hi>Fortunatianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leia,</hi> ſubſcribe to Hereſie, and conſequently could not be infallible. And though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> rely ſo much on the Authority of the Fathers, to ſupport and juſtifie the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of their <hi>Church,</hi> yet upon true Examination we ſhall find, they make no more for their Univerſal Biſhop,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:36427:76"/>than St .<hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Two Catholick Epiſtles</hi> do.</p>
            <p>And for their arguing out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s 55 <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> that ſure makes rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, than for them; for there St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes to <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but writes not ſo much to him, as of himſelf, who was Biſhop of <hi>Carthage;</hi> againſt whom a Faction of Schiſmaticks had ſet up another Biſhop: Now though the Papiſts ſay reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, that 'tis a mark of the Univerſal Biſhop, that other Biſhops ſhould make their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes unto the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet ſure 'twere better Reaſoning to conclude thus, If the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:36427:77"/>been acknowledged Univerſal Biſhop, and his Authority and Supremacy had been believ'd and own'd, ſure St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> had not been ſatisfied with onely barely writing him his ſad ſtory, (for he did no more,) but doubtleſs would have made his complaint to him, and deſired and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted redreſs from him, as Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhop over the whole <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> but his not doing ſo, argued he eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him Biſhop onely of one <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> all know, did reſolutely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Decree of the <hi>Roman Biſhop,</hi> and all that adhered to him in that one point of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36427:77"/>
               <hi>Rebaptizing,</hi> which the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Church</hi> at that time deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as a neceſſary Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Excommunicated the Biſhop of <hi>Cappadocia, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia,</hi> and all that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Tradition, and would not ſo much as allow them lodging or entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince the <hi>Papiſts</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that not to re-baptize thoſe, whom Hereticks had baptized, to be a damnable Hereſie. 'Tis well worth aſking the Papiſt, when this begun to be ſo; for if they ſay, from the beginning it was ſo, then they muſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a contradiction; for then was St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> a Profeſſor of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:36427:78"/>damnable Hereſie, and yet the <hi>Papiſts</hi> eſteem him a Saint and Martyr.</p>
            <p>And on the other ſide, if 'twere not ſo from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then did the <hi>Pope</hi> wrongfully excommunicate thoſe other <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> without ſufficient ground of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and ſeparation, which by their own Tenents, is ſchiſmatical; ſo let them chuſe which ſide they pleaſe, the <hi>Pope</hi> was in an errour.</p>
            <p>And though <hi>Victor Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> obtruded the <hi>Roman</hi> Tradition touching the time of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> upon the <hi>Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Biſhops,</hi> under the pain of Excommunication, and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:36427:78"/>Damnation; yet we read that <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and all the other Weſtern Biſhops, though they did agree with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> yet they did ſharply reprehend his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating the <hi>Aſian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, for their diſagreeing with him; which moſt plainly argues, that the Weſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops thought that not a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did; and therefore it muſt neceſſarily follow, they did not eſteem the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop infallible, nor the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> an Hereſie. And this I am ſure is true and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:36427:79"/>
            <p>The <hi>Popiſh</hi> Story tells us, That <hi>Optatus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> upbraided the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> as Schiſmaticks, becauſe they held no Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by adding afterwards that they were Schiſmaticks, for they held no Communion with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches of <hi>Aſiae,</hi> which occaſions this Queſtion of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> Whether a ſeparation from theſe ſeven <hi>Apoſtolick Churches,</hi> was a mark of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, or not; if they ſay it was not, how comes it that the Pope's Authority is a ſtronger Argument for the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church, than the <hi>Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Authority for the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches; And if the Papiſts
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:36427:79"/>ſay, a ſeparation from thoſe ſeven <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches was a mark of Hereſie, then they muſt confeſs their Church was for many years Heretical as ſeparating many years from the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Polycrates</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and Metropolitan of <hi>Aſia</hi> deſpiſed the <hi>Popes</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Supremacy and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and kept contrary to the <hi>Pope Eaſter-day,</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do ſo much quote the authority of the Fathers, yet I find they as little befriend their Churches infallibility, as the <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelúes have done, for though
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36427:80"/>the Papiſt ſay St. <hi>Hierome</hi> conceived it neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in matters of Faith, to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet before the <hi>Papiſt</hi> brag of that, let them anſwer us this, how came it then to paſs, that St. <hi>Hierome</hi> choſe to believe the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical upon the authority of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, and to reject it from the Canon of the <hi>Roman</hi> Churches Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And how comes it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he diſſented from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church touching the Canon of the old Teſtament, let the <hi>Papiſt</hi> take heed of loſing their Fort, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to maintain their out-works.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:36427:80"/>
            <p>And now to conclude this point, and excuſe the Papiſts miſtake concerning their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhop, we read in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who thought there was none left beſide himſelf in the whole Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had not revolted from God; and yet God himſelf is pleaſed to aſſure us he was deceived; And if a Prophet, and one of the greateſt err'd in his judgment, touching his own time and Country, why may not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> (ſubject to the ſame paſſions) err in their opinion, and judgment about the <hi>Popes</hi> being univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Biſhop, when plain reaſon tells them, as well as us, that
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:36427:81"/>there were other Biſhops as much univerſal as the. <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now come to examine this infallible <hi>Pope,</hi> whether he, cannot make his infallible I <hi>Church</hi> more infallible than he has made himſelf, and free the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church from error, though he could not the <hi>Pope</hi> from Hereſie.</p>
            <p>Now towards the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the pretended infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I lay this as the foundation of my diſcourſe, that the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a Congregation of men, whereof every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, not one excepted, and conſequently the generality, is nothing but a collection of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:36427:81"/>men, and if every one be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, <hi>(as who dare ſay he is free from ſin)</hi> how can the whole but be defiled with error; as reaſonably may a man brag he is in perfect health and ſtrength, and yet at the ſame time confeſs he hath not one ſound part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him. And truly it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much creates my wonder, but does not in the leaſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my reaſon, what the <hi>Papiſts</hi> can pretend by the infallibility of their <hi>church,</hi> for if they will allow their <hi>Pope</hi> to be no better than St. <hi>Peter</hi> was; their Church to be compoſed of no better men than the <hi>Holy Apoſtles</hi> were; I ſhall deſire no more,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:36427:82"/>and I am ſure they can never prove ſo much, for they that pretend to it, declare as great an <hi>ignorance,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>a ſin,</hi> in denying his Lord and Maſter: and there are many other known circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which made St. <hi>Paul</hi> prove him blame-worthy to his face.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> being in error, we have not onely the examples of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, who in the time of our <hi>Saviours</hi> Paſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcandalized, loſt their faith in him, and I believe the Papiſts will not ſay they could loſt their faith in our bleſſed <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> without error; and therefore our Saviour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36427:82"/>his Reſurrection upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with their increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and called <hi>Thomas</hi> incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous for denying the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in the Twentieth of St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further 'tis mod: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that the very <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, even after the ſending the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> did through inadvertency, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, continue ſometime in an error, contrary to a revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led truth; And if the Papiſts will not own to know this truth, they may be fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of it in the ſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> where they may plainly read that notwithſtanding our <hi>Saviours</hi> expreſs warrant and injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36427:83"/>to the <hi>Apoſtles to go and preach to all Nations.</hi> Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, till St. <hi>Peter</hi> was better informed by a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Heaven, and by the converſion of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> (both St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Church,</hi> held it unlawful for them to go and Preach the Goſpel to any but the <hi>Jewes.</hi> Now ſince we can prove that St. <hi>Peter</hi> did err, and that the Church compoſed partly of the <hi>Holy Apoſtles,</hi> themſelves, who were bleſſed with, and inſpired by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> could miſtake, and that <hi>there is no man free from ſin,</hi> and yet that the Body of men that make, up the <hi>popiſh Church</hi> ſhould be infallible, is I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36427:83"/>beſide my Faith, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, or reaſon to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
            <p>For ſure if the <hi>Roman</hi> Church had been eſteem'd by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> infallible, what needed the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> any other Creed, than this ſhort Creed, <hi>I believe the Roman Church</hi> infallible, and that would have been more effectual to keep the believers of it, from Hereſie, and in the true Faith, then this Apoſtolical Creed we now have.</p>
            <p>And ſure the <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot but believe with us, that thoſe holy men that wrote the New Teſtament, were not onely good men, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo men that were deſirous to
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:36427:84"/>direct us in the plaineſt and ſureſt way to Heaven. And the <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot alſo but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with us, that they were likewiſe men very ſufficiently inſtructed by the Spirit of God, in all the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry points of the Chriſtian Faith: Therefore certainly 'tis moſt: rational to believe, they could not be ignorant of this <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> that all Faith is no Faith, except we believe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was deſign'd by God to be the Guide of Faith, as the Church of <hi>Roome</hi> believes, and would have us believe ſo too.</p>
            <p>We alſo further believe, and that with great reaſon
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:36427:84"/>too, that the Writers of the New Teſtament were wiſe men, eſpecially being they were aſſiſted by the Spirit of wiſedom; and ſuch that muſt know, that an uncertain Guide was as bad as none at all; and yet after all this, is it poſſible for a Philoſophical or contemplative man; nay, for any man that has reaſon or common ſenſe, after all theſe ſuppoſitions, to believe that none among theſe holy Writers of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould remember, <hi>(ad rei memoriam,)</hi> To ſet down plainly this moſt neceſſary Doctrine, not ſo much as once, that we were to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible.</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:36427:85"/>
            <p>Again, that none of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> ſhould ſo much as once name this Popiſh neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point of Faith, if they had eſteem'd it neceſſary for us to believe it, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>He kept not back any thing that was profitable for us</hi> and ſure the Papiſts cannot deny, but what is neceſſary to ſalvation, muſt be very profitable: And St; <hi>Luke</hi> alſo plainly tells Chriſtians, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was <hi>to write all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi> And ſure it ſtands alſo with reaſon, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Remans,</hi> he would have congratulated this their extraordinary privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, if he had believ'd it belong'd to them.</p>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:36427:85"/>
            <p>And though the <hi>Romans</hi> bring it as a great Argument for them that St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells them, <hi>Their Faith is ſpoken all the world over.</hi> Yet pray let them moderate thoſe thoughts with this conſideration, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid the very ſame thing to the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and let them further conſider this, that if the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith had been the Rule of Faith for all the world for ever, as the Papiſts hold, ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have forborne to put the <hi>Romans</hi> in fear of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility (for though rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery is much in Faſhion now, ſure 'twas not then) that they alſo, nay the whole Church of the Gentiles, if
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36427:86"/>they did not lock to their ſtanding, might fall into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, as the <hi>Jews</hi> had done, 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>And methinks it alſo ſtands with great reaſon, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> writing ſo often of Hereticks, and Antichriſt, ſhould have given the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world this (as Papiſts pretend) onely ſure Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative from them, to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the infallible Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and not to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from it, upon the pain of damnation.</p>
            <p>Methinks alſo St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>Jude,</hi> in their Catholick <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> would not have forgot giving Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians this Catholick directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:36427:86"/>of following the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and St. <hi>John</hi> in ſtead of ſaying, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that Jeſus is the Chriſt, and born of God,</hi> might have ſaid, He that adheres to the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and lives according to it, is a good Chriſtian; and by this mark you ſhall know him. In a word, can there be any thing more irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, than to believe, that none of theſe holy men, who were ſo deſirous of mens ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ſhould ſo much as once remember to write, that we were to obey the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, but leave it to be collected from uncertain prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and by more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:36427:87"/>conſequences.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole, I cannot without much wonder, look on the <hi>Pope's</hi> confidence, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> credulity, in eſteeming the <hi>Pope</hi> or his Councils to be an infallible Guide; ſure either they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read what they ought to believe, or elſe they will not believe what they read, though it be never ſo known a Truth, and worthy of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: for if they did, they could never believe the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility of the Popiſh Church for indeed if they would read the Popiſh ſtory; or, as I may well call it, the Civil Wars of the Popes, you ſhall find, as I ſaid before, Pope
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:36427:87"/>againſt Pope, Councils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Councils; ſome Fathers againſt others, nay, ſome againſt themſelves; new Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions brought in, and old ones turn'd out; one Church againſt another; nay, the Church of one Age againſt the Church of another. In a word, the Papiſts ſay, their Church is infallible, and all other Chriſtians beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber than they, abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it; and yet we muſt for all that believe the Popiſh Church infallible.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeak the plain Truth, and in a word to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravel the real cauſe of the Grandeur of the Church of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:36427:88"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> above all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, is onely this; <hi>Rome</hi> was the Imperial Town of the Empire, and its Greatneſs was given by men, and not God; and when afterwards <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial City, they Decreed, that the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhould have equal Priviledges and Dignities with that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to end this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I deſire you will pleaſe to conſider this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion , which is, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all that the Papiſts have ſaid, be it never ſo much and mighty to ſhew the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility of their Church, I am verily perſwaded they
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:36427:88"/>cannot ſhew more, if ſo much, out of the Scriptures, for their Church, as the ſimal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſociety of Chriſtians met together in prayer, can for themſelves, <hi>that when two or three are met together in my name, I will be amongſt then ſayes the Lord.</hi> And now I have juſt done this ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the Sun is juſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on finiſhing this dayes viſit. I can very readily follow that holy advice of not <hi>letting it go down in my anger:</hi> (which I thank God I have to none living) and therefore am in ſo much Charity with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as to wiſh that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, nor <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> might waſt their pretious
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:36427:89"/>time in meer ſpeculative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about words: and ceremonies, which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will never carry us to Heaven; but that we may ſpend our time like wiſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the wayes, and fear of God, which is the onely beginning of wiſedom; and not conſume it in ſtudying and maintaining of Diſputes, and factions, but if we muſt ſtill differ, let <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> differ in opinions, but as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> did, who, though they were of differing Judgments touching the natures of <hi>Souls,</hi> yet both of them agreed in the main, that all men had <hi>Souls,</hi> and ſouls of the ſame nature.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:36427:89"/>
            <p>And as Phiſitians though they diſpute whether the Brain or the Heart be the principle part of man, yet that all men have Brains, and Heart they ſufficiently agree in; So though <hi>Proteſtants</hi> eſteem one part of the Church doctrine, and <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſet a higher value on another part, yet the Soul of the Church may be in both of them, and though the Papiſts account that a neceſſary truth, which the Proteſtants account nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neceſſary, nor perhaps true; yet in truth, truly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary they both agree, <hi>viz.</hi> The Apoſtles Creed, and that Faith, Hope, and Charity, are neceſſary to Salvation; And
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:36427:90"/>laſtly though <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold, they may be juſtified by their works, and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> hold none can be juſtified barely by them, (in regard of the imperfections of their works) yet on the other ſide, we ſo much agree with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as to eſteem none can be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified without them, for without Repentance, and Charity, none can be good, they being both like Health to our bodies, the want of which is ſufficient to diſturb all other pleaſures. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we read St. <hi>Pauls Treatiſe of juſtification by Faith, without the works of the Law.</hi> Let us at the ſame time read what he writes to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:36427:90"/>the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerning the abſolute neceſſity of that Excellent vertue of <hi>Charity,</hi> and they will reconcile one another; and I wiſh, <hi>that we were all ſo reconciled in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spirit, and in the bond of peace.</hi> And that you <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> may be the ſooner recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to me, for this tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I ſhall now make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which after ſuch an overgrown letter, muſt needs be the beſt complement that can be made by,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Madam</hi> yours <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date> the 24. <hi>of</hi> Feb. 1673</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36427:91"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36427:91"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
